Artificial intelligence updates
every week, Friday 2:00 p.m. Eastern,
today Friday, April 10. As usual, we
have a lot of updates. And the epigraph
for today's is intelligence is the
ability to adapt to change. This is
Stephen Hawking. Of course, we have a
lot of changes coming, but here is
another definition of intelligence
from
2013 by Linus Torvalds, creator of
Linux.
Intelligence is the ability to avoid
doing work yet getting the work done.
And yeah, periods of social instability
historically the best times for
individual growth.
Frightening, yes. Extraordinary
interesting, absolutely. As Benjamin
Franklin said, God helps those who help
themselves. So, this is time
to adapt to change and to do it very
fast.
And this is our leaderboard.
And this is from yesterday, April 9th.
We have the same players except just one
addition, which is from Meta, Muse
Spark. And you see it's here, pretty
high on the text side and a little bit
lower on the coding side, but they
specifically wrote that they're not
proud about their coding ability, but
they're working on it.
This model is proprietary. It's not open
source.
It looks like it's smaller and faster
than their previous models. It's very
token efficient. It
uses less tokens. And it's available on
all the apps like WhatsApp, Instagram,
whatever. If
it's available.
Anyway, the rest is basically the same.
So, Blue is Claude is the champion. And
Gemini is Google, also pretty good. Open
AI,
good at coding at least and open sources
green. This is GLM, which is all chain.
Okay. Next.
Wow, yeah. This
This is interesting. I love her movies.
This is a famous actress, Milla
Jovovich. And if you go to this GitHub
account, it has only one
repository
called Mem Palace,
which is mostly Python scripts which
create memory for your agent. You see
text stack, 54 Python files, 32 MD
files, skills, commands, and so on. So,
what they do? Think about Palace. And
Palace
may have
wings like big pieces of the palace and
then it may have halls, which are
smaller pieces, and then it have rooms,
which is even smaller pieces.
So, all it is is a hierarchical way to
store information.
And they actually store it in Chroma DB,
which is
very simple, well-known
database. Several years ago it used to
be only in memory. Wouldn't even write
into a file, but now it's
improved. They also use SQLite, which is
also light database for knowledge graph.
And Chroma DB they use as a vector
database. So, they store
embeddings to create vectors and they
can do semantic search and they can use
SQLite to do to follow knowledge graphs.
So, light solution using very light text
stack performs very well on memory
benchmarks. Like amazing achievement.
And yeah, the actual programmer is Ben
Sigman.
And
next is Anthropic managed agents. You
know, for example, in database, you can
install it on your server or you can
install it in the cloud on some server
or you can just
use managed instance of a database,
right? Where the cloud provider will
manage it for you. So, here we have the
same thing. You can install agent on
your desktop or you can install it on
some server or you can use managed agent
and Anthropic now provides those managed
agents.
And this is in public beta, but
available and yeah, this is this is
good. So, the pricing is the regular
Claude token rates plus 8 cents per
session hour
and and so on.
Okay. Agentic AI solutions. I was just
curious. Like everybody now says
that they have agent. And this craziness
started
well, the
the big explosion was in January. So,
first of all, Anthropic Claude desktop
announced some of their plugins and one
of them was
the legal work, like a legal assistant.
So, suddenly on your desktop you have a
legal assistant running. This actually
crashed
>> [laughter]
>> the software as a service market like
the stock market. It was
really big big event. Another big event
also in January, big explosion with open
claw, which is a
again desktop agent. Well, mostly people
install it on things like
Mac Mini and so on. So, it became very
very popular.
350 something thousand stars on on
GitHub already. Just absolutely
unbelievable. But there are so many
other
agents are now being provided. Like
everybody is claiming that they have a
good agent. There are here the links for
like awesome open claw alternatives or
awesome AI agents. There are multiple
multiple written in all kind of
languages. Now, Abacus, they had Abacus
deep agent, which is cloud-based, but
now they also have Abacus AI desktop
application, which behaves like this
similar to this. Now, Hermes now
becoming very very popular. It's a
similar to open claw, but its agent
learns over time, becomes better,
improves its own skills.
Cursor, you know, famous
development for coding.
Open AI operators of coming from Open
AI. Manus AI. Well, there are two
versions. One is from the original
company and another is from Meta.
And the Perplexity computer.
So, Perplexity is available in the
cloud, but also there is application
which you can pull from uh
Apple Store and and use it. So, they
have this
Perplexity XPS app and dedicated file
system MCP. So, again, Mistral from
France. They have Dev Stral desktop
capable coding agent. Gemini CLI, of
course, very famous, widely known and
used and can do a lot of stuff on your
computer. Then there are agents which
are cloud platform agents and there are
many of them.
And then there are things coming from
Asia, cloud platform like Tencent,
Alibaba, Baidu.
Then Europe, Mistral, Gemini agent,
different from US agent. Alpha,
AutoGenAI.
Then Apple intelligence, Deep Seek and
multi-on. And there are so many more.
This is just a very very short brief,
but this is the future coming, right?
I used to be a software engineer and I
say used to be because I'm not writing
code anymore. For real. Like 100% I'm
not writing code anymore.
So, this bad habit I had to write code,
it disappeared. I'm cured. So, well,
people also have bad habit of doing some
work on their computers, clicking the
mouse. Now, looks like this agents will
take over and remove your bad habit. So,
>> [laughter]
>> now you are just talking to the agent
and you becoming the teacher, the
organizer, the manager of the agent.
Okay, this is a plug shamelessly about
my channel. So, my name is Lev Selector.
So, channel name is also Lev Selector.
Well, I haven't updated the statistics.
It's now it's more than that.
You can download slides for all my
presentations. I provide links under.
And also I usually ask the question
under the video or in comments. Please
take a moment and answer the question.
Okay. Claude Buddy.
A virtual pet built into Claude code.
So,
Claude code is a terminal application.
So, it's a text-based and you can
activate the buddy. And buddy is just
something to have fun. So, it can
tease you,
make some funny comments and whatever.
>> [groaning]
>> Which Yeah, which
makes your work fun, which which is
good. And doesn't cost you tokens,
doesn't cost you anything and you can
turn it on and off.
Anthropic restricts third-party Claude
usage. So, because so many people with
open claw started using their max
subscriptions and it was hitting
Anthropic cloud.
So, they now explicitly forbid that.
Open claw updates.
I haven't updated today, so I don't
know. Maybe there was another update.
But you see the updates like April 8,
April 7, April 5. Like every day, every
second day, there are some updates with
open claw. And similar with Claude code
release.
There are every several days there are
updates. And this is a interesting
article, how Anthropic shipped 120
features in 90 days.
>> [snorts]
>> And the answer is they're using Claude
code
>> [laughter]
>> to write their their own applications
including Claude code.
Okay, this is interesting.
Oh, there's actually a link to the video
which I haven't posted, but
Matt Berman challenged the hacker to
hack his setup and he gave him only five
attempts and limited time. So, hacker
couldn't get in, couldn't hack his
system.
Anyway,
journey again coming from
Matt Berman because he's using open claw
and he created a lot of custom skills
and he wanted to share those skills or
abilities with other people and it's
kind of difficult because different
people have different setups. So, he
came up with the idea of something
called kit and kit is a combination
like including the read me with
instructions how to install these
abilities skills or whatever scripts are
required.
Uh, probably
the this kind of kits are not
standardized yet.
So, like you know, you have standards
for MCP servers. You have stand-
standards for
uh, skills for example, but you don't
have standards for
kits like reusable um, abilities which
agents can like
share, [snorts] but
this this is a good attempt.
Uh, okay, Google Gemini 4. There's a lot
of conversations about it. I think I
mentioned it last time and it's a open
source small models. So, the size the
the largest one is 31 billion parameters
and
they're quite capable on the level of
for example Quen 3.5 which is 400
billion parameters. You see or give me
K2 thinking. So, these are big models
and this small Gemini which is open
source and you can run it locally using
for example a llama. Uh, this this is
quite remarkable.
Um, open agents. So, this is a
multi-agent platform
which
uh,
where agents share same browser files
and chat context. Um, it's a Python SDK
multi-agent networking. So, this is how
you pip install open agents and how you
can use it.
Uh, it's Apache 2 open source.
Uh, next. Uh, Abacus co-work.
I was talking about Abacus deep agent
and now Abacus co-work. So, we have uh,
basically a desktop AI tool and it works
on Mac, Windows and Linux.
Uh,
yes, which is good because for example
Claude code and Claude desktop, they
only work on Mac.
Awesome design MD. So, this GitHub
repository which provides a lot of uh,
MD files. You can copy particular file
in your project and tell agent build me
a page that looks like that and it will
build you a pixel perfect UI.
Very useful if you are into design.
Meta Muse Spark. Uh, proprietary model.
So, it was just released couple days ago
and very little is known about it. Uh,
you saw it on leaderboard. It performs
very well.
Uh,
size is not clear.
Some people say that you need like 84
billion
um,
84 sorry
gigabyte
video memory to run it which may give
you some idea about the size.
Um, also nobody even knows the context
length. Some people say it's like 250
K. Some people say it's a million.
It's it's too new.
Uh,
but this is the first model produced by
this new group which is called super
intelligence labs led by Alexander Wang
in Meta.
And
yeah, it's it's it's fast. It looks like
it's smaller and capable
and it uses much less tokens than other
models
in in comparison. We will see. We'll
have more data next week. Okay,
Perplexity computer tax preparation. So,
this is my Perplexity screen and you see
this navigate my taxes and if you start
clicking here, it will lead you through
tax prep. It will ask you some numbers.
You can upload files and eventually it
can do your taxes, but this is only for
federal US taxes.
Um, Anthropic acquired Coefficient
Bio. It's a drug drug discovery company
for 400 million. This is stock
purchase. And yeah, this is this is a
big purchase.
Uh, deep learning NYU course.
Uh,
this course is 6 years old. Uh, like if
if you go to this link, you will see the
course like a navigable
website and this is GitHub uh,
with the original source files. And
the way it's done on GitHub, there's a
Jekyll process which can convert your
GitHub repository into
real
static living website.
Uh, pretty good. Maybe about 30 hours of
lectures and slides.
Uh,
and H claw free open source privacy
layer for AI agents.
Prevents sensitive data from reaching
the cloud. Uses three-tier system. Safe
requests go to cloud. Sensitive data is
sanitized and highly private like
passwords never leaves your device.
Okay, so this is a maybe good good thing
to use. Open claw plus a llama plus Quen
3.5.
So, you can use them together
and it gives you uh,
well
uh, a lot of ability. Anyway, next.
Uh, Anthropic versus Pentagon dispute.
Uh,
uh, well, you know what happened. There
was a hearing. Then judge gave
a week for government to appeal, but
they decided to come
well, to comply, but at the same time
they filed their
appeal which will take much longer, but
for now they removed their label, the
supply chain risk. Uh, so Anthropic can
continue working with the government.
Um, use Claude code with the Quen 3.6
plus model via Claude code router and
open router. So, Claude code actually
allows you to use
other models, not just Claude models and
this video describes
how to do it.
Not difficult.
Okay,
theory of inventive problem solving.
When I came
to US in '91, I had two books with me.
One was creativity as exact science by
uh, Genrich Altshuller. This is his
picture who created this theory of
inventive problem solving.
And
it's amazing. It's a very talented work
and there are so many followers, so many
companies which are using his
technology.
Um,
and it has really an algorithm how you
take a problem and you
go through certain algorithm to convert
it to a simplified
uh, like almost diagram representation
where the problem is and once you know
where the problem is, you can resolve
it.
He has like tables of different methods
of
resolving these problems.
And some of them are logical, some of
them maybe um, physics or chemistry or
electronics related, whatever.
So, there are many links. You you can
download the books. Many of them are
translated into English and there are
new books.
Um, what I did for fun, I made this
prompt. I want to create a skill for
Claude code named trees. Please create
skill MD file in standard format to use
with Claude. It should contain the
step-by-step instructions for using a
rease which is algorithm for
uh, inventive problem solving.
And yeah, and I got
I got the skill. So, I can do
Okay, next. Uh,
uh, here now. Again, this is another
project from Matthew Berman
and this is uh,
for now it's free. It's web hosting to
host information not for humans, but for
agents. So, the whole idea is that uh,
because most of the discovery and
purchases and many other things in like
two, three years from now will be
handled by agents. So, you need to
create web for agents and he provides
the platform for that.
Um, HeyGen avatar creator
was recently updated. So, from just one
photo and 15 second video, it can then
generate
a presentation. Julia McCoy makes her
videos. Her videos is about maybe 10
minutes, maybe more using this avatar
and now they're better quality and
easier to use. So, this is I think very
valuable information.
Um, Ola Lehmann
used counselor approach. This
this is great. This link, you see this
Google Docs.
It provides one text file which is
basically a skill or you can think about
it as a prompt.
So,
if you ask the question, this skill uses
five personalities. Contrarian, first
principle thinker,
expansionist, outsider, and executor.
So, these five personalities give five
answers. Then they look at each other's
answer and critique them like you do
cross review. And then finally, the
chairman look at all the output and
delivers the final result.
So, this is inspired by Andrej
Karpathy's LLM council concept. And the
author credited this method of helping
him choose a live workshop over the
self-paced course. And the decision
resulted in, well, good result, right?
Next,
Hermes agent, now becoming very very
popular.
What's the difference between Hermes and
Open Claw? Hermes can learn. It can
improve its own skills.
The core innovation is Kappa, a system
that automatically reviews tool calls,
identifies failures, updates its own
prompts similar to back propagation but
for behavior rather than model weights.
Over time, it builds memory, learns from
past conversations, and auto generates
reusable skills. Written in Python,
becoming very very very
popular.
This work is combination of Hermes
agents, but for memory,
it uses Karpathy's wiki idea. So, you
take markdown files or
Obsidian files, and you automatically
convert them into wiki, and then use
this wiki as memory. And this, by the
way,
so these are agent skills specifically
for Hermes.
And this is Anthropic.
Next, yes, more about this memory. So,
Karpathy's Obsidian
rack. Well, when you say rack, you you
basically mean searchable memory, right?
And his idea, you take Obsidian files
and then you create a wiki from it, and
then you use it from Claude code from
your agent. And people already created
this. Like, for example,
this open-source tool that turns any
folder into navigable knowledge graph
with a single command inside Claude
code. And yeah, very easy,
open-source, doesn't require
any enterprise setup, doesn't require
a vector database. What's interesting,
multiple solutions for for humans,
right?
Not for huge data sets where you
you need
semantic search and vector database. But
for so many small businesses and
personal systems, this is absolutely
enough. And
this is interesting. So, install
Obsidian, add a browser web clipper
extension, and then you
accumulate information in Obsidian raw
folder, and then Claude code,
you just instruct it to convert this
information into structured wiki. And
that's basically step-by-step how you
can easily set up it for yourself.
Okay, Microsoft
creating their own models,
which is M for Microsoft and AI. So, for
example, MAI transcribe, MAI voice, MAI
image. Cursor [snorts]
went through a major update.
And one of the things is that it was
completely rewritten into Rust. So,
remember Cursor originally was a fork
from Visual Studio Code, which was
written in TypeScript. So, now Cursor is
in Rust, and it has many other new
features and updates. Alibaba 12.1 AI
video model, open-source,
improved motion fluidity for clips up to
15 seconds at high resolution. You can
tweak first and last frames to to
dictate specific transitions and and and
so on.
Okay, Claude Microsoft 365 connector.
This is a read-only connector.
>> [snorts]
>> Remember Claude made deal with
Microsoft, so Microsoft can use Claude
in their copilot, but this is a little
bit different because this is access
from outside,
not from
inside application, but from outside.
But this is read-only.
Anthropic Claude Mythos, successor to
Claude Opus 4.6. So, Anthropic has this
new model called Mythos, which is
frighteningly how good it is.
And they don't release it. They used it
in project Glasswing with it's a cyber
cyber security with Microsoft, Google,
Cisco, Amazon, and Nvidia. But they
don't release it to the public because
they say
it is dangerous dangerously good and it
can be used for hacking. And
so, they're afraid of releasing it.
But very high scores on things related
to cyber security and software.
Caveman
plugin. So, this is a plugin for Claude
code, which converts
a lot of text which normal Claude
generates. So, here's like example, 69
tokens, into a very very short
representation, 19 tokens.
So, what happens as a result,
much
less tokens, right? So, up to 75
reduction in tokens.
But another thing, apparently, is when
you use less tokens,
your conversation become it's more
clarity. And because of that, less
errors and less hallucinations.
So, it's a additional benefit. So, maybe
everybody should use this Caveman
plugin.
Uh
Google coding agent version two called
Jitro. So, Jules
is Google's agent. I tried to use it
long time ago. I didn't like it, but now
they have this version two,
and
yeah, maybe it will be better. It's not
out yet. It should be released in May on
Google IO conference.
Flova AI video production platform. So,
apparently, this is all-in-one system.
It by itself substitutes many separate
tools, and you're paying like $19 a
month for using, but if if you would use
separate tools, then you would cost like
more than 100 a month. So, I guess
a good tool, production quality.
Digits. So, Digits is a AI-powered
accounting similar to QuickBooks,
and it can absolutely remove
all your worries about bookkeeping
because for it does, for example, auto
classifying at 97%
accuracy. No, let's put it this way. 97%
it just classifies by itself, and the
rest it asks the human
like to classify. It learns from your
firm's classification behavior, so
becomes better with time, automatic bank
reconciliation, and so on. So,
accounting is becoming AI.
Okay, these are jobs and layoffs. So far
in April,
nothing much is happening.
And
yeah, nothing here as as you can see.
And yeah, this is me as usual, and thank
you.